Have you ever wondered
if there’s a natural way
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that eating a diet
filled with animal products
can disrupt your microbiome faster
than taking an antibiotic?
Here’s our first story.
If you go online and search
for Crohn's disease and diet,
or ulcerative colitis and diet, the
top results are a hodgepodge
of conflicting advice.
What does the science say?
If you do a systematic review of
the medical literature on dietary
intake and the risk of developing
inflammatory bowel disease,
Crohn's disease is associated
with the intake of fat and meat,
whereas dietary fiber and
fruits appear protective.
The same foods are associated
with the other major inflammatory
bowel disease, ulcerative
colitis: fat and meat,
with a protective association
found for vegetable intake.
Why—according to this meta-analysis
of nine separate studies—
do meat consumers have
about a 50% greater risk
for inflammatory bowel disease?
Well, one possibility is that meat
may be a vehicle for bacteria
that play a role in the development
of such diseases.
Meat contains huge amounts
of Yersinia, for example.
Yes, maybe antibiotic residues
in the meat could be
theoretically kind of mucking
with our microbiome,
but Yersinia are so-called
psychrotrophic bacteria,
meaning they're able to grow
at fridge temperatures.
It has been found to be significantly
associated with inflammatory bowel
disease, supporting this
concept that Yersinia infection
may be a trigger for chronic
inflammatory bowel disease.
One reason why specifically
animal protein was associated
with triple the risk of
inflammatory bowel disease—
but plant protein was not—
is because it can lead
to the formation of toxic
bacterial end products,
such as the rotten egg
gas, hydrogen sulfide,
which is not just one of the main
malodorous compounds in human
flatus; it's a poison that has been
implicated in ulcerative colitis.
So go on some
meat-heavy, low-carb diet
and we're not just talking about
some malodorous rectal flatus,
but increased risk of irritable bowel,
inflammatory bowel syndrome,
and eventually colorectal cancer.
Hydrogen sulfide in the colon comes
from sulphur-containing amino acids
like methionine that are
concentrated in animal proteins,
though there are also sulfites
added as preservatives
to some nonorganic wine
and nonorganic dried fruit.
But it's the sulphur-containing
amino acids that may be the more
important of the two. Give people
increasing quantities of meat,
and you can get an exponential
rise in fecal sulfides.
Specific bacteria, like Biophilia
wadsworthia, can take this sulfur
that ends up in our colon and
produce hydrogen sulfide.
And give people an animal product-
based diet packed with meat
and eggs and dairy, and
you can specifically increase
the growth of this bacteria. People
underestimate the dramatic effect
diet can have on our gut bacteria.
Give people a fecal transplant
and it can take three days
to shift your microbiome.
Take a powerful antibiotic like
Cipro and it can take a week.
But start packing in the meat and
eggs, and within a single day
you can change your microbiome—
and not for the better.
You can more than double
the bad bacterial machinery
that churns out hydrogen sulfide,
consistent with the thinking
that diet-induced changes
to the gut flora may contribute
to the development of
inflammatory bowel disease.
In other words, the increase in
sulfur compounds in the colon
when you eat meat is not only
of interest in the field of flatology:
the study of human farts.
In our next story,
we look at how plant-based diets
can be 98% effective
in keeping ulcerative colitis
patients in remission,
blowing away other treatments.
One of the most common questions
physicians treating patients
with inflammatory bowel disease
(IBD) are asked is whether
changing one's diet can positively
affect the course of their disease?
Traditionally, our answer
had been, "We have no clue,"
but this may now be changing,
given the evidence that hydrogen
sulfide may be playing
a role in ulcerative colitis.
And since the sulfur-containing
amino acids concentrated in meat
cause an increase in colonic
levels of this rotten egg gas,
maybe we should take off the meat.
See, animal protein isn't just associated
with an increased risk of getting
inflammatory bowel disease
in the first place, but also IBD
relapses once you have the disease.
This is a recent development. Because
the concept of IBD as a lifestyle disease
mediated mainly by a Westernized diet
is not widely appreciated, an analysis
of diet in the follow-up period after
diagnosis in relation to a relapse
of inflammatory bowel disease has
been ignored. But not any longer.
Ulcerative colitis patients in remission
and their diets were followed for a year
to see which foods were linked to the
bloody diarrhea coming raging back.
And the strongest relationship between
a dietary factor and an increased risk
of relapse observed in this study
was for a high intake of meat.
So, what if you have people lower
their sulfur-containing amino acid intake
by decreasing their consumption
of animal products? They tried it
on four ulcerative colitis patients,
and without any change in meds,
they experienced like a four-fold
improvement in their loose stools.
In fact, they felt so much better
that they didn't think it ethical
to try switching them back.
Since sulfur-containing amino acids are
the primary source of dietary sulfur,
a low sulfur diet essentially means
a shift from a typical diet high
in animal protein and fat, and low in
fiber, to more of a plant-based diet.
Westernized diets
are pro-inflammatory,
and plant-based diets
are anti-inflammatory.
Let's see what treatment with
a plant-based diet can do, after
the onset of ulcerative colitis during
a low-carbohydrate weight-loss diet.
A 36-year-old man lost 13
pounds on a low-carb diet,
but also lost his health,
diagnosed with ulcerative colitis.
Put him on a diet centered around
whole plant foods, though,
and poof—symptoms resolved
without medication. Okay, but this is
just one case. I mean, case reports
are like glorified anecdotes.
The value of case reports lies in
their ability to inspire researchers
to put it to the test, and
that's exactly what they did.
There had never been a study published,
focusing on using plant-based diets
for the treatment of
ulcerative colitis until now.
Considering the lack of a suitable
diet to be the biggest issue faced
in the current treatment of
inflammatory bowel disease,
and regarding it as a lifestyle disease
caused mainly by our omnivorous diet,
a group of Japanese gastroenterologists
have been providing a plant-based diet
to all patients with IBD for over a
decade, and publishing extraordinary
results, far better than have to date
been reported in the medical literature.
I profiled some of the early work in
one of my first videos that went up
on NutritionFacts.org, found to
be effective in the maintenance
of remission in Crohn's disease
by 100% at one year,
90% at two years.
So how about a plant-based diet for
relapse prevention in ulcerative colitis?
Educational hospitalization meant
bringing patients into the hospital
to control their diet
and educate them
about the benefits
of plant-based eating,
so they'd be more motivated
to continue it at home.
Most patients—about three-quarters—
experienced improvements
such as disappearance or decrease
in bloody stool during hospitalization.
Fantastic! Okay, but here's the
really exciting part. Then they followed
the patients for 5 years, and 81%
were able to remain in remission
the whole time, and 98% were able to keep
the disease at bay for at least a year.
I mean that blows other treatments away.
Those relapse rates are far lower
than those reported with medication.
Under conventional treatment, other
studies found that about half relapse,
compared to only 2% among
those taught to eat healthier.
A plant-based diet was previously shown
to be effective in both the active and
quiescent stages of Crohn's disease.
The current study has shown that a
plant-based diet is effective in both
the active and quiescent stages
of ulcerative colitis as well.
And so they did another study on
even more severely affected cases
with active disease
and found the same thing,
far beating out
conventional drug therapy.
People felt so much better, they
were still eating more plant-based
even 6 years later.
The researchers conclude that
a plant-based diet is effective
for treating ulcerative colitis
to prevent a relapse.
Why? Well, plant-based diets are rich
in fiber, which feeds our good gut bugs.
That might partly explain why
a plant-based diet prevents
a variety of chronic diseases.
And so that's what we may be seeing
with inflammatory bowel disease,
suggesting that replacing an omnivorous
diet with a plant-based diet
is the right approach. It's like using
plant-based diets to treat
the cause of heart
disease, our #1 killer.
Not just safer and cheaper,
but works better.
No adverse side effects
noted for plant-based eating.
Let's compare that to the side
effects of immunosuppressants
used for ulcerative colitis, like
cyclosporine. Side effects include...
And now we have even fancier drugs
that cost about $60,000 a year
that s $5,000 a month and
they don't even work very well,
with clinical remission at 1 year
of only like 17 to 34%.
And instead of no adverse side
effects, they can give you a stroke.
They can give you heart failure.
They can even give you cancer,
including a rare type of cancer
that often results in death.
Or how about a serious brain disease
known as progressive multifocal
leukoencephalopathy,
which can kill you,
and for which there is
no known treatment or cure.
Yeah, yeah, increased risk of death,
but did we mention how nice and small
the pill was and the easy-to-open bottle?
Finally today,
we look at how switching
to a plant-based diet
has been shown to achieve
far better outcomes
than those reported on
conventional treatments
in both active and quiescent stages
in both Crohn’s disease
and ulcerative colitis.
Important to our understanding
and prevention of the global increase
in inflammatory bowel disease, we know
that dietary fiber appears to reduce risk,
whereas dietary fat, animal protein,
and sugar may increase risk.
"Despite the recognition of the
westernization of lifestyle as
a major driver of the growing incidence
of inflammatory bowel disease,
no countermeasures against such lifestyle
changes have been recommended,
except that patients with Crohn's
disease shouldn't smoke."
Look, we know consuming
whole, plant-based foods
is synonymous with an
anti-inflammatory diet.
So how about putting a
plant-based diet to the test?
Just cutting down on red and
processed meat didn't work,
but what about cutting
down on all meat?
A 25-year-old guy diagnosed
with Crohn's disease,
but failed to enter clinical remission
despite standard medical therapy.
But after switching to a diet based
exclusively on grains, legumes—
like beans, split peas, chickpeas,
and lentils—vegetables, and fruits,
he entered clinical remission,
without the need for medication
and showed no signs of Crohn's
disease on follow-up colonoscopy.
It's worth delving into
some of the details.
The conventional treatment they started
him on is infliximab, sold as REMICADE,
which can cause a stroke, and may
increase your chances of getting
lymphoma and other cancers—but
it's a bargain for only $35,000 a year.
And it may not even work
in 35 to 40% of patients,
and that seemed to be the case
here, so they upped the dose
after 37 weeks, and still suffering
after two years on the drug—
until he tried completely eliminating
animal products and processed foods
from his diet—finally experiencing
a complete resolution of his symptoms.
Prior to this, his diet had
been a typical American diet.
But having experienced complete
clinical remission for the first time
since his diagnosis, he decided
to switch to a whole-food,
plant-based diet permanently, severely
reducing his intake of processed food
and limiting animal products
to one serving, or less, per week.
And whenever his diet started to slip,
symptoms started coming back.
But he could always wipe
them out by eating healthier.
After six months of implementing
these changes in diet and lifestyle,
including stress relief and exercise,
a follow-up demonstrated complete
mucosal healing of the gut lining with
no visible evidence of Crohn's disease.
We know a diet consisting of whole
grains, legumes, fruits, and vegetables
has been shown to be helpful in the
prevention and treatment of heart
disease, obesity, diabetes,
hypertension, gallbladder disease,
rheumatoid arthritis,
and many cancers.
Although further research is required,
this case report suggests
that Crohn's disease might be
added to this list of conditions.
But that further research
has already been done!
About 20 patients with Crohn's disease
were placed on a semi-vegetarian diet,
meaning no more than a half-
serving of fish once a week
and a half-serving of meat
once every two weeks,
and achieved 100% remission rate
at one year, and 90% at two years.
Some strayed from the diet though.
Let's see what happened to them.
After a year, half had relapsed, and at
year two only 20% remained in remission.
But those that stuck with
it had remarkable success.
It was a small study with
no formal control group,
but represents the best reported
result in Crohn's relapse prevention
published in the medical
literature to date.
Nowadays, Crohn's patients are often
treated with so-called biologic drugs,
expensive injected antibodies that
suppress your immune system
and have effectively induced
and maintained remission
in Crohn's disease,
but not in everyone.
The current remission rate in Crohn's
with early use of REMICADE: 64%.
So 30 to 40% of patients are likely to
experience a disabling disease course
even after treatment. So what
about adding a plant-based diet?
Remission rates jumped up to 100%
for those who didn't have to drop out
due to drug side effects. Even
if you exclude the milder cases,
100% of those with serious, even severe
fulminant disease achieved remission.
But if you look at gold standard
systematic reviews, they conclude
that the effects of dietary interventions
on inflammatory bowel diseases,
Crohn's disease and ulcerative
colitis, are uncertain.
This is because only randomized
controlled trials were considered.
Totally understandable, as that's
the most rigorous study design.
Nevertheless, people with inflammatory
bowel disease deserve advice
based on the 'best available evidence'
rather than no advice at all.
And switching to a plant-based diet
has been shown to achieve
far better outcomes than those
reported on conventional treatments
in both active and quiescent stages
in both Crohn's and ulcerative colitis.
Maybe we should recommend plant-based
diets for inflammatory bowel disease.
It would seem clear that treatment
based on treating the cause
of the disease is optimal.
Spreading the word about healthier
diets could help halt the scourge
of inflammatory bowel, but how
are people going to hear about
this amazing research without some
kind of public education campaign?
That's what NutritionFacts.org
is all about.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.